Guide to the Consumer Reports. National Association of Consumers records, 1937-1964 and undated RL.11818
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports. National Association of Consumers records
1937-1964 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports (Firm)
RL.11818
3.0 Linear Feet
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. The National Association of Consumers was a consumer advocacy and lobbying organization founded in 1946 and active until around 1957-1958. The National Association of Consumers records include correspondence, drafts and notes for articles and speeches, meeting minutes, membership lists, bylaws and other printed materials that primarily document the administrative life of the organization. Included in the collection are correspondence and writings of Colston Warne and Helen Hall, and food safety projects relating to the pork and poultry industry, including Trichinosis. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized alphabetically.
Biographical / Historical
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. The National Association of Consumers was a consumer advocacy and lobbying organization founded in 1946 and active until around 1957-1958.
The National Association of Consumers (NAC) formed in 1946 as a private-sector initiative to continue the consumer advocacy work of the Office of Price Administration's Consumers Advisory Committee when the government agency was disbanded after World War II. Helen Hall, vice chairperson of the Consumer Advisory Committee and director of the Henry Street Settlement, was named president of the NAC. Membership in the organization consisted of both individuals and local chapters, made up of existing consumer organizations as well as newly formed organizations. Originally headquartered in Washington, D.C., the NAC moved to the Henry Street Settlement in New York and later to Amherst, Mass. The NAC was a registered lobbyist that advocated for a wide range of issues, including food standards, product labeling, rent control, milk prices as well as for the creation of Cabinet-level consumer protection agencies. The NAC's status as a lobby eventually restricted its ability to secure private-sector funding and its viability declined through the 1950s. In 1955 the NAC reorganized as an educational corporation and pursued a merger with the Council on Consumer Information, which never materialized. Dr. William Haller, an economist at Dickinson College, took on the role of executive secretary in 1955, but NAC operations stalled and the organization was effectively inactive around 1957.
Source: Consumer Reports, historical note on National Association of Consumers, Consumer Reports Archives records.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Consumer Reports. National Association of Consumers records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Consumer Reports Archives records
Consumer Reports. Board of Directors records
Consumer Reports. Colston E. Warne papers
Collection Overview
The National Association of Consumers records include correspondence, drafts and notes for articles and speeches, meeting minutes, membership lists, bylaws and other printed materials that primarily document the administrative life of the organization. Included in the collection are correspondence and writings of Colston Warne and Helen Hall, and food safety projects relating to the pork and poultry industry, including Trichinosis.
Consumer advocacy; consumer protection; Consumers -- United States; Lobbying; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; National Association of Consumers
- Organizational Records, 1937-1964 and undated; 1
  - Board of Directors--Bylaws, statements, etc., 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors--Bylaws, statements, etc., 1955 (Box 8)
  - Board of Directors--Minutes, 1946-1957 and undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1950 Apr.; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1956 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1950 May-1953; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1964 and undated; 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence--Colston Warne speaking trips, 1946-1951 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence--Governor's survey, 1955-1956 (Box 4)
  - Educational activities--Book club, 1949-1950 (Box 4)
  - Educational activities--Course: "Your Money's Worth", 1950 (Box 4)
  - Finances, 1947-1956 (Box 4)
  - Finances--Lobbying Act report, 1950 (Box 8)
  - Government activities--Consumer Advisory Committee, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Government activities--Legislation, testimony, etc., 1940-1958 (Box 4)
  - Government activities--Legislation, testimony, etc., 1953 (Box 8)
  - Government activities--National Conference on Trichinosis, 1952-1954; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Government activities--Poultry Industry Advisory Committee, 1948-1953 (Box 4)
  - Government activities--Poultry Industry Advisory Committee, 1948-1954; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Leases, 1947 (Box 8)
  - Membership/Subscriptions--Contacts, 1947 (Box 5)
  - Membership/Subscriptions--Correspondence, 1948-1950 June; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Membership/Subscriptions--Correspondence, 1950 July-1961 and undated; 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Membership/Subscriptions--Lists, 1947-1957 (Box 6)
  - Press releases and clippings, 1937-1958 (Box 6)
  - Press releases and clippings, 1937-1958 (Box 8)
  - Publications--Local chapters--Cincinnati Consumer Conference materials, 1946-1955 (Box 6)
  - Publications--Local chapters--St. Louis Consumer Federation, 1949-1956 (Box 8)
  - Publications--National, 1946-1956 (Box 6)
  - Publications--National, 1947-1953 and undated (Box 8)
  - Publications--Notes and drafts, undated (Box 7)
  - Radio forum--What's On Your Mind, 1948 (Box 7)
  - Writings and speeches--Helen Hall, 1947-1950 (Box 7)
  - Writings and speeches--Others, 1937-1952 (Box 7)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes contributions by Colston Warne, Elizabeth Rohr, Mary Dublin Keyserling, and Persia Campbell